<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Business &#8211; Vivasoft</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/business/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Top Software Company with Talented Geeks</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 08:31:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/cropped-feb-icon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Business &#8211; Vivasoft</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Blockchain Is Helping Improve Business Operations Worldwide</title>
		<link>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/</link>
					<comments>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 08:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blockchain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10273</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blockchain technology is often associated with cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin. However, the potential applications of this technology have increased over the years and go far beyond cryptocurrencies.  With the ever-digitizing world, businesses are beginning to adopt new technologies to streamline their operations into future-ready outfits. One of the most talked-about technologies in the business fraternity to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology is often associated with cryptocurrencies like <a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Bitcoin</a>. However, the potential applications of this technology have increased over the years and go far beyond cryptocurrencies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the ever-digitizing world, businesses are beginning to adopt new technologies to streamline their operations into future-ready outfits. One of the most talked-about technologies in the business fraternity to digitally transform them has been blockchain.</span></p>
<p><strong>But what exactly is blockchain? </strong></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Introduction: What Is Blockchain?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In simple terms, or as they say, blockchain for dummies, is a digital ledger used to record transactions between two parties. Then the catalog is distributed across computer networks, making it virtually impossible to tamper with. It has led to the popularity and demand of technology, so much so that it is being taken up by businesses all over the world to improve operations and create new opportunities. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite its potential, blockchain technology is still in its early stages. This article will explore how businesses use blockchain technology worldwide and its benefits.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">What Are the Benefits of Using Blockchain for Business? </span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In recent years, there has been a lot of hype around blockchain automation and its perks for businesses.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The technology is secure, and tamper-proof is something that comes to mind immediately. Still, in the bigger picture, it has so much more to offer to revolutionize how businesses operate. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Below are some of the benefits of using Blockchain:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced security </strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology is highly unassailable and inviolable, making it ideal for sensitive data and information of companies.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Greater transparency</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain allows all involved parties to see and track transactions, ensuring greater transparency and accountability. It helps in building trust between the parties.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster transactions</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is an ideal platform for businesses to track their contracts and other data, which helps streamline and speed up the process, saving businesses time and money.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reduced costs</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain can help reduce the costs of traditional mediators, such as banks and brokers.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced data integrity</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain’s decentralized nature helps protect data from being tampered with or corrupted, which reduces the risk of fraud and provides businesses with a secure way to depot data.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All this can contribute to the success of the companies by transforming them away from classic methods that often are a drag on performance. Many small and large businesses around the world are benefiting from blockchain technology in multiple ways, some of which are discussed below.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Different Ways Businesses are Using Blockchain</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you are considering using blockchain for your startup, you are definitely on the right track. While initially designed as the infrastructure for Bitcoin, blockchain is now being used by businesses for a variety of purposes. From supply chain management to data security, there are many ways that blockchain can help your business. In some cases, blockchain is even being used to create entirely new business models. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Below are examples of how businesses utilize the blockchain to improve their operations:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Digital Identity</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many firms use blockchain to create digital identities for individuals and businesses. It helps them with online KYC (know your customer) processes.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Supply Chain Management</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is being widely used to track the movement of goods through the supply chain, from raw materials to the final product. It allows businesses to ensure that their products come from certified suppliers and meet all quality standards.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Payments</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has taken over the process of payments and settlements of many companies. It has proven to reduce costs and improve efficiency.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Asset Management</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has beautifully forged the future of asset management. The technology has assisted businesses in building a dispute-less environment as consensus-based automation involves all the parties for any update to the asset records. It has also given way to a range of innovative investments. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Digital Tokens</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is also being used to create digital tokens. These tokens can represent assets such as currency, property, shares, and more. They can also help in developing loyalty programs and decentralized power applications.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other Ways</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some businesses are using blockchain to create a secure, decentralized database. It can be used to store data such as customer records, financial transactions, and more. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other businesses are using blockchain to create digital contracts. It can be used to streamline the contract process and create smart contracts that automatically execute when certain conditions are met.</span></p>
<h4><strong>Examples of some of the well-known blockchain companies are: </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Walmart</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Microsoft</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Intel</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">PayPal</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ripple</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Coinbase</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">and IBM</span></li>
</ul>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are There Any Challenges With Blockchain Businesses?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite the potential benefits of using blockchain for businesses, there are also some challenges that need to be considered. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scalability</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of them is the scalability of blockchain, which needs to be addressed. It works fine for a small network; however, if the number of people increases, the process, like transitions, takes longer to operate, resulting in higher transaction costs. Therefore the mass integration makes it less lucrative for bigger companies.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forks</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another challenge is the potential for forks, which makes the system volatile. A disagreement among developers to implement an upgrade or not can lead to two distinct versions of a particular project, namely soft and hard forks which results in chaos and confusion.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This makes the system vulnerable to attacks, and often users and companies lose their money due to them. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Safety</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although blockchain is often touted as being secure and tamper-proof, there are still some challenges that businesses need to be aware of when using this technology. One of the biggest challenges is the fact that blockchain is still relatively new and untested. Companies need to be mindful of the risk of cyberattacks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite these challenges, blockchain remains a promising option for businesses. Many people are still optimistic about the potential of blockchain and are investing in this technology. With time, proper planning, careful execution, and further development, it is possible that businesses can address and overcome these challenges and use blockchain to their advantage.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Skepticism towards any new change is typically considered normal, especially if it relates to your investment. While blockchain applications are ever expanding, one should consider talking to those thriving with this technology to make a final decision. I often wonder if Satoshi Nakamoto knew of this breakthrough technology&#8217;s potential. As technology continues to evolve in the coming years, we will see blockchain being used in numerous other sectors.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>6 Facts Why You Should Outsource from Bangladesh</title>
		<link>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/</link>
					<comments>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 08:36:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8981</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we look at the world and advance, we observe a virtual competition worldwide. And about outsourcing, we can barely find a country out of the boundary of this. However, several facts work as the calibers and our today&#8217;s consideration is one of the rising flames of the virtual world is Bangladesh.  Nonetheless, we must [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When we look at the world and advance, we observe a virtual competition worldwide. And about outsourcing, we can barely find a country out of the boundary of this. However, several facts work as the calibers and our today&#8217;s consideration is one of the rising flames of the virtual world is Bangladesh. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nonetheless, we must disclose the capabilities before anything an apt country requires to be appointed. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladesh has a massive population, and the atmospheric standards for the vast majority of the literate section make it much easier for them to find out employment opportunities for outsourcing work at the present time. Consequently, enormous numbers of citizens from different countries are racing to serve you the best.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Facts Why You Should Outsource From Bangladesh</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Till now, we learned about Bangladesh as a new sun of the IT industry. But, there might be some questions you may face when selecting Bangladesh as your working partner. Such as why you should consider the people of this country, what can be the foremost benefit you will get, and many more.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let&#8217;s find out the pillars behind this selection:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cost Efficient</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The biggest advantage of Bangladesh outsourcing is cost-efficiency. Naturally, it costs businesses in the United States, the UK, Canada, and Australia less to outsource to the Bangladesh than to staff their employees locally, even at the very start. Once a company outsources to Bangladesh, it can save as much as 70% of overall cost. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The study of technology and engineering is currently a popular endeavor among engineering students. So, if you are looking for an erudite nation with a vast knowledge of different resources at a efficient cost, Bangladesh would be the best source.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Better Value For The Quality And Consistent High-Quality Services</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The people of Bangladesh are enormously dedicated to their work. Moreover, they are even determined to pay extra hours to ensure output quality. Besides, they are not those who protest against any unexpected situation. Generally, they wait until it turns atrocious for them. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A set of good ramifications require a brunch of seamless effort. Sometimes we need to blend more spices into our work to make it extraordinary. And the good news is Bangladeshis are highly competent, and by birth, they adapt to the nature of developing the best possible fruits. As a result, the quality of work and dedication remain standstill. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, you can blindly rely on the people of Bangladesh while asking for the best output and consistent performance. Indeed, you will find more than your expectations.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If we consider the countries with the most educated citizens, Bangladesh is one of them. On average, more than 90% of citizens in the workforce are highly educated. Besides, English is as important as their mother tongue, and above 50% of the educated class can communicate through English fluently. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, when you are communicating with an employee from Bangladesh, you do not require any extra capabilities to make them understand the work. Moreover, their welcoming behavior will introduce a new ease to you. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eventually, if you desire a great communicative patron, a Bangladeshi can be the ideal one. It is worth mentioning that the accent they use is either British or American, which is entirely different from the countries of the same horizon like Vietnam, the Philippines, African countries, etc.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladeshis Are Flexible </span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you are looking for a person to be a partner to guide you towards your aim, Bangladeshis are one of the nations that can take part. A prevalent characteristic of Bangladeshis is working beyond the requirement. Moreover, they are highly adaptive to new disciplines, making them extraordinary to work as partners. They will adjust their routine according to your needs. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When your work requires extra hours often, a Bangladeshi can be the optimal choice to handle your utter project. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Political And Economic Stability</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The political environment of Bangladesh will serve you the ease of having your partner without any hesitation. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the fascinating facts about Bangladesh, the government itself promotes outsourcing tasks to have stable foreign relationships. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recently, the government announced a tax-free scheme till 2025 for the people who are currently working for outsourcing tasks. According to this theory, you can quickly enter the labor market of Bangladesh and hire an employee according to your requirements. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Technological Advancements</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladesh is one of those countries which belongs to the list of developing countries. And the foremost reason behind this is the adaptive quality towards technological advancement. Therefore, the devices of the majority are fantastic to use, and the mental improvements are notable. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even Bangladesh is a prime location to outsource to. They&#8217;re one of the strongest rivals in the worldwide IT enterprise market.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
