<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Nafayeth &#8211; Vivasoft</title>
	<atom:link href="/author/nafayeth/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Top Software Company with Talented Geeks</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 09:36:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/cropped-feb-icon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Nafayeth &#8211; Vivasoft</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How Blockchain Is Revolutionizing the Digital World</title>
		<link>/blog/how-blockchain-is-revolutionizing-the-digital-world/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blockchain]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=11155</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Just a few years ago, we used to talk about how blockchain will impact industries and the way they perform soon. A couple of years later, here we are in awe of how it has succeeded in helping upscale the way businesses work today and is continuing to make a rapid change in the world. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Just a few years ago, we used to talk about how blockchain will impact industries and the way they perform soon. A couple of years later, here we are in awe of how it has succeeded in helping upscale the way businesses work today and is continuing to make a rapid change in the world. The widespread adoption of this cutting-edge technology is swiftly taking over almost all firms.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the best things about blockchain is that regardless of how vague your area of interest is, you can put it into use. Whether it is the secure storage of money or an efficient platform for trading energy, it can do what no other technology has been able to do before. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An affordable and fair way for people to interact without interference from third parties is all that is needed, and the blockchain technology serves it like none other.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The endless potential of the innovative technology is due to the three main features:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Secure, Efficient, and Decentralized</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These top specifications of blockchain have made it an advanced infrastructure. The security, reliability, and cost-efficiency of blockchain compared to traditional processes in unmatched.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The most significant impact the features hold in the modern world is how it is changing how we do business. </span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has ensured a risk-free digital platform where transactions are secure, transparent, and immutable. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">There is no need for third-party involvement, which leaves the users in complete control of their assets. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Its decentralized nature makes it virtually impossible to hack or corrupt the database, and its transparency is what allows people to check the authenticity and validity of the data registered within their system. </span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These features are just a fraction of what makes Blockchain so incredible.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The use of blockchain technology for multiple purposes in different sectors has proven to be an efficient alternative to the classic methods. Below are some well-known applications of technology that have played a significant role in revolutionizing the world.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Applications of Blockchain Technology</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain-based applications are already being used in healthcare, finance, automotive, and pharma fields. It has streamlined processes that have traditionally been time-consuming, expensive, and prone to corruption.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the Automotive Industry</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">At first glance, blockchain might appear completely different from the current technology used for car manufacturing, but the case is otherwise. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This innovative technology is being implemented in the automotive industry to improve it for both traditional players and new entrants alike. The car industry has always been one of the most important industrial areas for any economy, which is why its development has been a priority for governments at all levels.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Over the years, several successful attempts have made digitalization an essential element of car manufacturing. It has been a major step towards increasing productivity since it enables manufacturers to use a series of data models to help them make better quality products. It has also helped manufacturers reduce costs and increase customer satisfaction rates regarding product quality and delivery time.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Real Estate</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The automotive industry is not the only one that is making use of this disruptive technology. Blockchain technology has immense potential to disrupt the real estate industry. The five primary applications of blockchain technology in the real estate sector are as follows:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Property titles</span></h3>
<p>You can use blockchain to ensure that all parties can access accurate and reliable property titles. It will help eliminate fraud, a significant problem in the current system. It can also help bring down the transaction costs.</p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Escrow</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It is used to create a tamper-proof escrow system that records all transactions related to a property sale, including title transfers and payments made by buyers and sellers. It will ensure that all parties involved in the transaction have complete transparency concerning the progress of their respective deals.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Property Management</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has the potential to streamline property management processes by making them more efficient and transparent than they are today. It is done through its ability to record high volumes of data securely in real-time without any need for manual input or human intervention from anyone other than authorized network participants (i.e., brokers, escrow agents, developers). This capability allows for efficient record keeping, tracking, and reporting on various aspects of any project.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">In IoT Businesses</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Internet of Things (IoT) is a technology that has been around for a long time. IoT encompasses everything from smart home appliances to self-driving cars and drones. Unsurprisingly, the IoT is at the forefront of blockchain adoption because it has many potential applications in this industry.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology is changing how IoT devices interact with each other and is used to improve efficiency in IoT business models by making them more secure, transparent, and efficient. It is also used to create new business models by solving problems that plagued the industry for years, such as data privacy and trust. These changes are transforming how we live by improving productivity and services in many industries.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">In Healthcare Sector</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The prominent application of blockchain technology in healthcare is patient data storage and sharing. As a result of the growing popularity of electronic medical records (EMR), patients are increasingly requesting access to their medical records. This data is often stored on-site or off-site at multiple organizations, including hospitals, insurance companies, and home health agencies.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">To protect patient privacy, these parties must share only relevant information about each patient. However, if a patient has multiple visits to different providers within a short time, it becomes difficult for all parties involved to manage this data correctly. In addition, there are instances where hospitals may be obligated by law to maintain these records but don&#8217;t have sufficient resources to do so.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology can help solve these problems by providing an immutable record of all transactions related to a patient&#8217;s care that can be verified by any party who needs access to those records without compromising their privacy or security.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">These and many other sectors benefit from innovative technology by decreasing the unnecessary hassle of everyday work and increasing their revenues. You can </span><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="/contact" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><b>hire a blockchain developer</b></a></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to help your company convert to modern work means and outshine your competitors.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While regular people are gradually becoming aware of this innovative technology already being used in the healthcare sector and has been slated for use in the agriculture sector and government services, most people haven&#8217;t yet decided on its real-world use.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has an almost infinite range of applications and will likely change our world in many ways down the road. It is indeed what will take the digital world to the next level. Some predict that blockchain will usher in new economic and public systems as the Internet did, but even faster.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Blockchain Is Helping Improve Business Operations Worldwide</title>
		<link>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/</link>
					<comments>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 08:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Blockchain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10273</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Blockchain technology is often associated with cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin. However, the potential applications of this technology have increased over the years and go far beyond cryptocurrencies.  With the ever-digitizing world, businesses are beginning to adopt new technologies to streamline their operations into future-ready outfits. One of the most talked-about technologies in the business fraternity to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology is often associated with cryptocurrencies like <a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Bitcoin</a>. However, the potential applications of this technology have increased over the years and go far beyond cryptocurrencies. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the ever-digitizing world, businesses are beginning to adopt new technologies to streamline their operations into future-ready outfits. One of the most talked-about technologies in the business fraternity to digitally transform them has been blockchain.</span></p>
<p><strong>But what exactly is blockchain? </strong></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Introduction: What Is Blockchain?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In simple terms, or as they say, blockchain for dummies, is a digital ledger used to record transactions between two parties. Then the catalog is distributed across computer networks, making it virtually impossible to tamper with. It has led to the popularity and demand of technology, so much so that it is being taken up by businesses all over the world to improve operations and create new opportunities. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite its potential, blockchain technology is still in its early stages. This article will explore how businesses use blockchain technology worldwide and its benefits.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">What Are the Benefits of Using Blockchain for Business? </span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In recent years, there has been a lot of hype around blockchain automation and its perks for businesses.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The technology is secure, and tamper-proof is something that comes to mind immediately. Still, in the bigger picture, it has so much more to offer to revolutionize how businesses operate. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Below are some of the benefits of using Blockchain:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced security </strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain technology is highly unassailable and inviolable, making it ideal for sensitive data and information of companies.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Greater transparency</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain allows all involved parties to see and track transactions, ensuring greater transparency and accountability. It helps in building trust between the parties.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster transactions</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is an ideal platform for businesses to track their contracts and other data, which helps streamline and speed up the process, saving businesses time and money.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reduced costs</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain can help reduce the costs of traditional mediators, such as banks and brokers.</span></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced data integrity</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain’s decentralized nature helps protect data from being tampered with or corrupted, which reduces the risk of fraud and provides businesses with a secure way to depot data.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All this can contribute to the success of the companies by transforming them away from classic methods that often are a drag on performance. Many small and large businesses around the world are benefiting from blockchain technology in multiple ways, some of which are discussed below.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Different Ways Businesses are Using Blockchain</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you are considering using blockchain for your startup, you are definitely on the right track. While initially designed as the infrastructure for Bitcoin, blockchain is now being used by businesses for a variety of purposes. From supply chain management to data security, there are many ways that blockchain can help your business. In some cases, blockchain is even being used to create entirely new business models. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Below are examples of how businesses utilize the blockchain to improve their operations:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Digital Identity</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many firms use blockchain to create digital identities for individuals and businesses. It helps them with online KYC (know your customer) processes.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Supply Chain Management</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is being widely used to track the movement of goods through the supply chain, from raw materials to the final product. It allows businesses to ensure that their products come from certified suppliers and meet all quality standards.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Payments</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has taken over the process of payments and settlements of many companies. It has proven to reduce costs and improve efficiency.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Asset Management</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain has beautifully forged the future of asset management. The technology has assisted businesses in building a dispute-less environment as consensus-based automation involves all the parties for any update to the asset records. It has also given way to a range of innovative investments. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Digital Tokens</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blockchain is also being used to create digital tokens. These tokens can represent assets such as currency, property, shares, and more. They can also help in developing loyalty programs and decentralized power applications.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other Ways</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some businesses are using blockchain to create a secure, decentralized database. It can be used to store data such as customer records, financial transactions, and more. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Other businesses are using blockchain to create digital contracts. It can be used to streamline the contract process and create smart contracts that automatically execute when certain conditions are met.</span></p>
<h4><strong>Examples of some of the well-known blockchain companies are: </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Walmart</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Microsoft</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Intel</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">PayPal</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ripple</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Coinbase</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">and IBM</span></li>
</ul>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Are There Any Challenges With Blockchain Businesses?</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite the potential benefits of using blockchain for businesses, there are also some challenges that need to be considered. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Scalability</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of them is the scalability of blockchain, which needs to be addressed. It works fine for a small network; however, if the number of people increases, the process, like transitions, takes longer to operate, resulting in higher transaction costs. Therefore the mass integration makes it less lucrative for bigger companies.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Forks</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another challenge is the potential for forks, which makes the system volatile. A disagreement among developers to implement an upgrade or not can lead to two distinct versions of a particular project, namely soft and hard forks which results in chaos and confusion.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This makes the system vulnerable to attacks, and often users and companies lose their money due to them. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Safety</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Although blockchain is often touted as being secure and tamper-proof, there are still some challenges that businesses need to be aware of when using this technology. One of the biggest challenges is the fact that blockchain is still relatively new and untested. Companies need to be mindful of the risk of cyberattacks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite these challenges, blockchain remains a promising option for businesses. Many people are still optimistic about the potential of blockchain and are investing in this technology. With time, proper planning, careful execution, and further development, it is possible that businesses can address and overcome these challenges and use blockchain to their advantage.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Skepticism towards any new change is typically considered normal, especially if it relates to your investment. While blockchain applications are ever expanding, one should consider talking to those thriving with this technology to make a final decision. I often wonder if Satoshi Nakamoto knew of this breakthrough technology&#8217;s potential. As technology continues to evolve in the coming years, we will see blockchain being used in numerous other sectors.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/how-blockchain-is-helping-improve-business-operations/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reliable UDP (RUDP): Can UDP be made reliable?</title>
		<link>/blog/can-udp-be-made-reliable/</link>
					<comments>/blog/can-udp-be-made-reliable/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 07:07:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Programming & Development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The major decision has to be made for the real-time application is which transport protocol will be used, as some features demand reliability, some need real time effects. Beyond these, developers had to develop an optimized solution so that user can use the application in low bandwidth efficiently, reducing user handset&#8217;s power consumption, and also [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The major decision has to be made for the real-time application is which transport protocol will be used, as some features demand reliability, some need real time effects. Beyond these, developers had to develop an optimized solution so that user can use the application in low bandwidth efficiently, reducing user handset&#8217;s power consumption, and also using peer-to-peer communication system where possible.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong>Popular Communication Protocols:</strong></h3>
<p>TCP and UDP are the most commonly used ones.</p>
<p>TCP provides a reliable connection and is used by the majority of current Internet applications. TCP, besides being responsible for error checking and correcting, is also responsible for controlling the speed at which this data is sent. TCP is capable of detecting congestion in the network and will back off transmission speed when congestion occurs. These features protect the network from congestion collapse. As TCP provides features such as congestion control, it would be the preferred protocol to use. Unfortunately due to the fact that TCP is a reliable service, delays will be introduced whenever a bit error or packet loss occurs. This delay is caused by retransmission of the broken packet, along with any successive packets that may have already been sent. This can be a large source of jitter. TCP uses a combination of four algorithms to provide congestion control, slow start, and congestion avoidance, fast retransmit and fast recovery. These algorithms all use packet loss as an indication of congestion, and all alter the number of packets TCP will send before waiting for acknowledgments of those packets. These alterations affect the bandwidth available and also change delays seen on a link, providing another source of jitter. Combined, TCP raises jitter to an unacceptable level rendering TCP unusable for real-time services. And also affects handset&#8217;s power consumption.</p>
<p>UDP is a thin layer on top of IP that provides a way to distinguish among multiple programs running on a single machine. UDP also inherits all of the properties of IP that TCP attempts to hide. UDP is therefore also a packet based connectionless, best-effort service. It is up to the application to split data into packets, and provide any necessary error checking that is required. Because of this, UDP allows the fastest and most simple way of transmitting data to the receiver. There is no interference in the stream of data that can be possibly avoided. This provides the way for an application to get as close to meeting real-time constraints as possible. UDP however provides no congestion control systems. A congested link that is only running TCP will be approximately fair to all users. When UDP data is introduced into this link, there is no requirement for the UDP data rates to back off, forcing the remaining TCP connections to back off even further.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><b>What is RUDP?</b></h3>
<p>In summary, TCP is easy because it works in all cases, but it is less efficient because of that. On the other hand, UDP either needs its applications to be resilient to loss or the application developer needs to write in a system for ensuring that missing/corrupted packets are retransmitted. And such systems are in effect proprietary RUDP. RUDP is used in many famous projects, such as Google&#8217;s QUIC and WebRTC.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-10248 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/What-is-RUDP.png" alt="What is RUDP" width="848" height="448" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/What-is-RUDP.png 848w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/What-is-RUDP-480x254.png 480w" sizes="(min-width: 0px) and (max-width: 480px) 480px, (min-width: 481px) 848px, 100vw" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><em><u>Diagram: &#8211; What is RUDP?</u></em></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong>Why RUDP?</strong></h3>
<p>Now we will take a look how RUDP can solve <strong>Latencies in Network Games.</strong></p>
<p>One of the major problems in network games has been that of latency (lagging) that game<br />
technology researchers are still tackling. Latency largely affects user satisfaction and it is often caused by insufficient hardware capacity or the internet speed that the user is employing. Even though online games are becoming more complex and the number of participants in these games is increasing continuously, users cannot properly deal with the requirements to play these games, as system upgrades and subscription changes to a higher speed internet service are costly. Instead of passing such a burden on to the users, the game companies should instead invest in providing an improved communication algorithm.</p>
<p>When RUDP is ideally implemented, it is possible to distinguish between the information essential and non-essential for playing games even if it has been lost. Also, the essential information can be distinguished into the cases where its order is guaranteed or unguaranteed. Actually, since the amount and the frequency of these non-essential packets being lost during<br />
communications are low, they can be effective when they are used appropriately. The data which is to be transmitted repeatedly can be renewed/updated even if it is lost and the information which does not largely affect the visual component (e.g., the movement of an unnoticeable character at the edge of the screen, etc.) should be utilized more actively.</p>
<p>Unlike TCP, it is possible that the delay caused by momentary packet error in the network (latency) can be reduced a little. For instance, supposing that the information (low-reliability + no order) of the characters A, B, and C have died in sequence has been transmitted by the server, it will not be so strange in the game that the characters B and C would die first followed by A when the information is used regardless of its credibility and order. In the case where TCP is used, the information of A will be retransmitted first and all the characters will die later. In other words, if the process is implemented with TCP only, the delay will not only occur for B and C but also for all the actions taking place after their death. Actually, UDP can be used widely in games as it has fewer constraints between the personal networks.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, RUDP is introducing the concept ‘Reliable state’ in addition to 3 data types.<br />
For example, when the state has been changed as A → B → C, any re-transmission request will<br />
not be requested even when only A has been received followed by C, skipping B. Therefore, RUDP is optimized for making the most of its characteristics of maintaining the latest information with reliability while maintaining the main concept of the game.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="wp-image-10249 size-full aligncenter" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/RUDP-Work-Flow.png" alt="RUDP Work Flow" width="758" height="544" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/RUDP-Work-Flow.png 758w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/08/RUDP-Work-Flow-480x344.png 480w" sizes="(min-width: 0px) and (max-width: 480px) 480px, (min-width: 481px) 758px, 100vw" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><em><u>Diagram: &#8211; RUDP Work Flow</u></em></strong></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The game companies and their researchers are still dealing with one of the major issues in their gaming software, the latency or the lagging. A variety of factors (e.g., hardware capacities, internet connections, etc.) are involved in this issue and its effect is growing larger as the online games are becoming more complex and sophisticated allowing more participants to join them. Although the game companies encourage or recommend the users to upgrade their systems or change internet service providers to solve the problem, they still need to consider the situation where their customers would not be able to afford costly upgrades or move to an expensive internet service. This will definitely affect their sales policy so that they are consistently looking for a more efficient way of stabilizing the gaming speed without actually forcing the customers to make changes. One of the major problems involved with gaming speed has been the communication algorithm, and the communication protocol in particular.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/can-udp-be-made-reliable/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>6 Facts Why You Should Outsource from Bangladesh</title>
		<link>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/</link>
					<comments>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 08:36:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8981</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When we look at the world and advance, we observe a virtual competition worldwide. And about outsourcing, we can barely find a country out of the boundary of this. However, several facts work as the calibers and our today&#8217;s consideration is one of the rising flames of the virtual world is Bangladesh.  Nonetheless, we must [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When we look at the world and advance, we observe a virtual competition worldwide. And about outsourcing, we can barely find a country out of the boundary of this. However, several facts work as the calibers and our today&#8217;s consideration is one of the rising flames of the virtual world is Bangladesh. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nonetheless, we must disclose the capabilities before anything an apt country requires to be appointed. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladesh has a massive population, and the atmospheric standards for the vast majority of the literate section make it much easier for them to find out employment opportunities for outsourcing work at the present time. Consequently, enormous numbers of citizens from different countries are racing to serve you the best.</span></p>
<h2><span style="font-weight: 400;">Facts Why You Should Outsource From Bangladesh</span></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Till now, we learned about Bangladesh as a new sun of the IT industry. But, there might be some questions you may face when selecting Bangladesh as your working partner. Such as why you should consider the people of this country, what can be the foremost benefit you will get, and many more.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Let&#8217;s find out the pillars behind this selection:</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cost Efficient</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The biggest advantage of Bangladesh outsourcing is cost-efficiency. Naturally, it costs businesses in the United States, the UK, Canada, and Australia less to outsource to the Bangladesh than to staff their employees locally, even at the very start. Once a company outsources to Bangladesh, it can save as much as 70% of overall cost. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The study of technology and engineering is currently a popular endeavor among engineering students. So, if you are looking for an erudite nation with a vast knowledge of different resources at a efficient cost, Bangladesh would be the best source.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Better Value For The Quality And Consistent High-Quality Services</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The people of Bangladesh are enormously dedicated to their work. Moreover, they are even determined to pay extra hours to ensure output quality. Besides, they are not those who protest against any unexpected situation. Generally, they wait until it turns atrocious for them. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A set of good ramifications require a brunch of seamless effort. Sometimes we need to blend more spices into our work to make it extraordinary. And the good news is Bangladeshis are highly competent, and by birth, they adapt to the nature of developing the best possible fruits. As a result, the quality of work and dedication remain standstill. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, you can blindly rely on the people of Bangladesh while asking for the best output and consistent performance. Indeed, you will find more than your expectations.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Communication</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If we consider the countries with the most educated citizens, Bangladesh is one of them. On average, more than 90% of citizens in the workforce are highly educated. Besides, English is as important as their mother tongue, and above 50% of the educated class can communicate through English fluently. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, when you are communicating with an employee from Bangladesh, you do not require any extra capabilities to make them understand the work. Moreover, their welcoming behavior will introduce a new ease to you. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Eventually, if you desire a great communicative patron, a Bangladeshi can be the ideal one. It is worth mentioning that the accent they use is either British or American, which is entirely different from the countries of the same horizon like Vietnam, the Philippines, African countries, etc.</span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladeshis Are Flexible </span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When you are looking for a person to be a partner to guide you towards your aim, Bangladeshis are one of the nations that can take part. A prevalent characteristic of Bangladeshis is working beyond the requirement. Moreover, they are highly adaptive to new disciplines, making them extraordinary to work as partners. They will adjust their routine according to your needs. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When your work requires extra hours often, a Bangladeshi can be the optimal choice to handle your utter project. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Political And Economic Stability</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The political environment of Bangladesh will serve you the ease of having your partner without any hesitation. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the fascinating facts about Bangladesh, the government itself promotes outsourcing tasks to have stable foreign relationships. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Recently, the government announced a tax-free scheme till 2025 for the people who are currently working for outsourcing tasks. According to this theory, you can quickly enter the labor market of Bangladesh and hire an employee according to your requirements. </span></p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">Technological Advancements</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bangladesh is one of those countries which belongs to the list of developing countries. And the foremost reason behind this is the adaptive quality towards technological advancement. Therefore, the devices of the majority are fantastic to use, and the mental improvements are notable. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Even Bangladesh is a prime location to outsource to. They&#8217;re one of the strongest rivals in the worldwide IT enterprise market.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/facts-why-you-should-outsource-from-bangladesh/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shaping the Future: 8 Challenges Every Software Developer Faces &#038; How to Overcome them</title>
		<link>/blog/8-challenges-every-software-developer-faces-and-how-to-overcome-them/</link>
					<comments>/blog/8-challenges-every-software-developer-faces-and-how-to-overcome-them/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nafayeth]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 11:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Personal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8878</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Software developers are one of the most important people in the technology industry. They face many challenges, but their work is essential to the success of technology companies. Developers are responsible for creating and maintaining software applications. They work with teams of engineers and designers to create products that solve problems and improve efficiency. Despite [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Software developers are one of the most important people in the technology industry. They face many challenges, but their work is essential to the success of technology companies. Developers are responsible for creating and maintaining software applications. They work with teams of engineers and designers to create products that solve problems and improve efficiency.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite the importance of their work, developers often face difficult challenges. They must be able to understand complex technical problems and find creative solutions. They also need to be able to communicate effectively with other members of a development team. In addition, they must be able to keep up with rapidly changing technology trends.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The challenges that developers face can be difficult, but they are also very rewarding. When a developer creates a new application or solves a difficult problem, they make an important contribution to the success of their company.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Software development has come a long way since the early days of computers. However, there are still many unsolved challenges that confront developers every day. </span></p>
<h2><strong>Here are 8 of the most pressing issues that software developers need to keep in mind:</strong></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><b>1. Staying updated with the evolving technology:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the world today, technology is constantly evolving. What was once cutting edge is now outdated. Keeping up with the latest trends and technologies can be a daunting task, but it is important in order to stay competitive in the job market and connect with friends and family. There are many ways to stay current with technology, both big and small.</span></p>
<h3><b>2. Learning new programming languages:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In order to stay ahead of the curve in the programming industry, it&#8217;s important to learn new programming languages. With new languages being created every year, it can be tough to keep up. But with the right tools and resources, anyone can learn a new language.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One great way to learn a new language is through online courses. There are many websites that offer free or paid courses in various programming languages. Another option is to watch video tutorials on YouTube or other online video platforms. Books are also a great way to learn a language; many books come with exercises and quizzes to help you practice what you&#8217;ve learned.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another way to improve your skills in a programming language is by coding communities. These are online forums where people from all over the world come together to share their code, ask questions, and give feedback.</span></p>
<h3><b>3. Building robust applications:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many different ways to build an application. Some applications are more robust than others. A robust application can withstand a lot of different types of abuse. It can also handle a lot of different types of errors. In order to build a robust application, you need to have a good understanding of how the application will be used. You also need to have a good understanding of the underlying technologies that are being used.</span></p>
<h3><b>4. Dealing with difficult code:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are many difficult code problems that can arise when you are programming. Sometimes, the code is just difficult to read and understand. Other times, the code may be buggy or have unexpected results. In any case, it is important to know how to deal with difficult code problems.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The first step is to try to understand the problem. This may require reading the code more than once, and it may help to draw a diagram or write out what you think the code should do. Once you have a good understanding of the problem, you can start trying to fix it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Often, fixing a difficult code problem will require debugging techniques such as stepping through the code line by line or using print statements to see what is happening. You may also need to modify the code in order to make it easier to understand and fix.</span></p>
<h3><b>5. Collaborating with other programmers: </b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you&#8217;re a programmer, sooner or later you&#8217;ll need to collaborate with other programmers. Whether you&#8217;re working on a team project or just helping someone else with their code, collaboration is essential for success. But it can also be difficult, especially if you&#8217;re not used to working with others. The good news is that there are many tools available to help you work more effectively. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the most useful is source control. You can think of source control as a way to keep track of all your changes to a piece of code, and then share them with others so they can make their own changes without getting confused. This is a fundamental part of the open-source development process.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Collaborating with other senior programmers can help keep your skills sharp and introduce you to new techniques. When working with others, be sure to set expectations early on about what you hope to get out of the collaboration. It&#8217;s also important to be respectful of others&#8217; time and abilities and be willing to compromise when necessary. By collaborating with other seniors, you&#8217;ll not only improve your own skills but also build strong relationships that can benefit you in the future.</span></p>
<h3><b>6. Maintaining a positive attitude:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Computer programming can be a challenging and frustrating task. It is easy to become negative and give up when problems arise. However, maintaining a positive attitude is key to success as a programmer. When you are positive, you are more likely to keep trying until you find a solution. You will also be more motivated to learn new things and improve your skills. A positive attitude also helps when working with others; it creates a more pleasant work environment and makes it easier to get along with others.</span></p>
<h3><b>7. Remaining organized:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a programmer, it is important to be organized. This means keeping track of your work and the files that you are working on. One way to do this is to use a source control system such as Git or SVN. These systems allow you to keep track of your changes and merge changes from other developers. They also allow you to go back to earlier versions of your code if needed.</span></p>
<h3><b>8. Developing a personal brand:</b></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a programmer, you are probably familiar with the importance of developing a strong personal brand. A personal brand can help you stand out from the competition and land your dream job. But how do you go about developing a personal brand? Here are a few tips:</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;">Figure out what makes you unique. What sets you apart from other programmers? What are your strengths and weaknesses?</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;">Create a portfolio that showcases your work. This can include project descriptions, screenshots, and videos of your work in action.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;">Get involved in the programming community. Attend conferences, write blog posts, and participate in online forums and discussion groups.</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;">Be active on social media. Platforms like Twitter and LinkedIn offer great opportunities to share your work and connect with other programmers.</span></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/blog/8-challenges-every-software-developer-faces-and-how-to-overcome-them/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
